<doc xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">

  <title>Bender Functional Core</title>

  <section>
    <title>Preliminaries</title>
    <h:p>We use a loose notation to describe the data and processing model of
      Bender in terms of objects and prototype, and an implied standard library
      for processing lists, managing DOM elements, &amp;c.</h:p>
    <h:ul>
      <h:li>The data model is defined in terms of <def>Object</def>s and
        <def>data</def>. Objects are defined by their <def>properties</def>. A
        property has a name and a value, which may be any <ref>data</ref>: a
        boolean, a number, a string, a number, an <ref>Object</ref>, or the
        undefined value.</h:li>
      <h:li>The binary operator <h:code>is-a</h:code> checks if the
        <ref>Object</ref> on the left-hand side was created from the
        <ref>Object</ref> on the right-hand side.</h:li>
      <h:li>A function is described by its name, formal parameters, and an
        optional return type. The pseudo-code used is a simple expression-based
        language with a liberal syntax that allows side effects, namely the
        mutation of object properties, and may not return any value.</h:li>
      <h:li><h:em>O</h:em> <h:code>&lt;</h:code> <h:em>P</h:em> means that the
        object <h:em>O</h:em> is <def>created</def> from the object
        <h:em>P</h:em>. <h:em>O</h:em> inherits all of the properties of
        <h:em>P</h:em>, along with their values. <em>O</em> may have additional
        properties, and may override any property of <em>P</em>.</h:li>
      <h:li><h:em>O</h:em><h:code>.</h:code><h:em>x</h:em> means the property
        <h:em>x</h:em> of object <h:em>O</h:em>.</h:li>
      <h:li><h:code>?</h:code> means that the property may be undefined. The
        operator <h:code>defined</h:code> checks if a value is defined.</h:li>
      <h:li><h:code>*</h:code> means a list or set of zero or more
        objects.</h:li>
      <h:li><h:code>+</h:code> means a list or set of one or more
        objects.</h:li>
      <h:li><h:code>[]</h:code> means an empty list.</h:li>
      <h:li><h:code>"..."</h:code> means a string (which can be considered as a list
        of characters.)</h:li>
      <h:li><h:em>L</h:em> <h:code>:</h:code> <h:em>x</h:em> means appending
        <h:em>x</h:em> to the list <h:em>L</h:em>.</h:li>
      <h:li><h:code>::</h:code> is the concatenation of two lists.</h:li>
      <h:li><h:code>&lt;-</h:code> means setting a property of an object on the
        left-hand side to the value on the right-hand side.</h:li>
      <h:li><h:code>=</h:code> is used for binding (in definitions and
        <h:code>let</h:code> forms) or equality testing.</h:li>
    </h:ul>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Nodes</title>

    <api>
      <h:p>The Bender data model deals with two kinds of tree structures: trees
        of <def>component</def>s, defining the high-level structure of a Bender
        application; and trees of <def>element</def>s, defining the contents and
        layout of a given <ref>component</ref>. Together, these trees define a
        <def>component graph</def>. Both trees are defined by tree
        <ref>Node</ref>s.</h:p>
      <h:div>
        <h:pre><def>Node</def> &lt; <ref>Object</ref>
  <ref>Node</ref>?    parent
  <ref>Node</ref>*    children
  string?  name</h:pre>
        <h:ul>
          <h:li><h:code>parent</h:code> is the parent <ref>Node</ref>, if any,
            of the node. The <def>root</def> of a tree has no parent.</h:li>
          <h:li><h:code>children</h:code> is the list of child <ref>Node</ref>s
            of the node.</h:li>
          <h:li><h:code>name</h:code> is an optional name for the node, that can
            be used in a <def>selector</def> to identify it. It can be any
            non-empty string and must be unique within a <ref>component
              graph</ref>.</h:li>
        </h:ul>
        <h:pre>  <ref>Node</ref>     insert_child(<ref>Node</ref> child)
  <ref>Node</ref>     remove_child(<ref>Node</ref> child)</h:pre>
        <h:ul>
          <h:li><h:code>insert_child</h:code> inserts a new child at the end of
            the list of children of the node and returns the added child.
            <todo>Insert before a reference Node, or at a given
              index.</todo></h:li>
          <h:li><h:code>remove_child</h:code> removes the child node from the
            list of children of the node and returns it.</h:li>
        </h:ul>
      </h:div>
    </api>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Components</title>

    <api>
      <h:p>The <def>Component</def> is the basic unit of functionality in
        Bender. Components are defined in terms of other components, both
        through <h:em>composition</h:em> (a component may contain child
        components) and <h:em>inheritance</h:em> (a component may inherit from a
        prototype component.) A <def>component tree</def> is a tree of
        Component nodes, the root of which is a <def>root component</def>. A
        <def>component graph</def> is a graph of nodes including the root
        component tree and its <ref>view tree</ref>. The component graph does
        not include nodes from the prototype of the component, or the prototypes
        of any of its children.</h:p>
      <h:div>
        <h:pre><ref>Component</ref> &lt; Node
  <ref>Component</ref>?  prototype
  data*       properties
  <ref>View</ref>        view
  <ref>Watch</ref>*      watches</h:pre>
        <h:ul>
          <h:li><h:code>prototype</h:code> is the <ref>Component</ref> that this
            component inherits from, if any. The prototype component must be a
            <ref>root component</ref>, <ie/> it must not have a
            <h:code>parent</h:code>. The <def>prototype chain</def> is the
            sequence of <h:code>Component</h:code>s formed by the prototype and
            its prototype chain. The prototype chain must not contain any cycle,
            <ie/> a component cannot inherit from itself, either directly or
            indirectly. <todo>Do <h:code>Component</h:code>s inherit from a
              fundamental component by default?</todo></h:li>
          <h:li><h:code>properties</h:code> is the list of all property values
            for this component, indexed by their name. From this list, the set
            of <def>defined properties</def> can be derived, and is the set of
            property names for the component. A property name can be any
            non-empty string. <todo>All properties of a component are “public”.
              However, having private properties would be useful; the set of
              properties could then be split in two, a set of public properties,
              and a set of private properties. The set of public properties
              would be inherited, while the set of private properties would not
              be inherited.</todo></h:li>
          <h:li><h:code>view</h:code> is the root of the <def>view tree</def> of
            this component. A component always has a view, but it may be a
            default view. <todo>We may allow components to not have a view;
              then they are still part of the component tree, but not the view
              tree and are not rendered but still cloned when the component is
              rendered.</todo></h:li>
          <h:li><h:code>watches</h:code> is the set of the <ref>Watch</ref>es of
            the component.</h:li>
        </h:ul>
        <h:pre>  <ref>Component</ref>   clone(<ref>View</ref> view)
  boolean     conforms(<ref>Component</ref> component)
  void        notify(string type, Object args)</h:pre>
      </h:div>
    </api>
    <h:p>A Component <h:em>C</h:em> is said to <def>conform</def> to the
      prototype of another component <h:em>P</h:em> if and only if
      <h:em>C</h:em> is <h:em>P</h:em>, or the prototype <h:em>C’</h:em> of
      <h:em>C</h:em> conforms to the prototype of <h:em>P</h:em>.</h:p>
  </section>

  <section>
    <title>View Elements</title>

    <section>
      <title>View</title>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Content</title>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>DOMElement</title>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Attribute</title>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Text</title>
    </section>

  </section>

  <section>
    <title>Watches</title>
  </section>

</doc>
